Narrator: 4
Leaving prison
Speaker: At the end of their sentence, most prisoners will be released.
Some may get parole and be released early for good behaviour,
if they agree to abide by certain conditions,
such as staying within a certain area and not going out at night.
They may have to wear an electronic tag, usually an ankle bracelet,
which allows them to be tracked.
After release, ex-offenders can find it difficult to reintegrate into society.
They often have difficulty finding work, and earn less money when they do.
They experience a wide range of medical and psychological issues, and many reoffend.
There are cases where prisoners have managed to obtain a retrial
and proved that they have been wrongfully convicted.
In such cases, a pardon is granted by the government
(in the USA, by the governor of the state), the sentence is quashed,
and they are likely to receive substantial compensation.